<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Vol. 1., No. 1, January 1977</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="25"/>
			<div type="title">
				<bibl>
					<title>Women and Honor: Some Notes on Lying</title>
					<author>Adrienne Rich</author>
				</bibl>
			</div>
			<div type="essay">
				<p>(These notes are concerned with relationships between and among women. When
					"personal relationship" is referred to I mean a relationship between two women,
					it will be clear in what follows when I am talking about women's relationships
					with men.)</p>

				<p>The old, male idea of honor. A man’s “word" sufficed —to other men — without
					guarantee.</p>

				<p>"Our Land Free, Our Men Honest, Our Women Fruitful" — a popular colonial toast in
					America.</p>

				<p>Male honor also having something to do with killing: I couid not love thee, Dear,
					so much / Lov'd I not Honour more (“To Lucasta, On Going to the Wars”). Male
					honor as something needing to be avenged: hence, the duel.</p>

				<p>Women’s honor, something altogether else: virginity, chastity, fidelity to a
					husband. Honesty in women has not been considered important, We have been
					depicted as generically whimsical, deceitful, subtle, vacillating. And we have
					been rewarded for lying.</p>

				<p>Men have been expected to tell the truth about facts, not about feelings. They
					have not been expected to talk about feelings at all.</p>

				<p>Yet even about facts they have continually lied. We assume that politicians are
					without honor. We read their statements trying to crack the code. The scandals
					of their politics: not that men in high places lie, only that they do so with
					Such indifference, so endlessly, still expecting to be believed. We are
					accustomed to the contempt inherent in the political lie.</p>

				<p>To discover that one has been lied to in a personal relationship, however, leads
					one to feel a little crazy.</p>

				<p>Lying is done with words, and also with silence.</p>

				<p>The woman who tells lies in her personal relationships may or may not plan or
					invent her lying. She may not even think of what she is doing in a calculated
					way </p>
				<p> A subject is raised which the liar wishes buried. She has to go downstairs, her
					parking-meter will have run out. Or there is a telephone call she ought to have
					made an hour ago.</p>

				<p>She is asked, point-blank, a question which may lead into painful talk: “How do
					you feel about what is happening between us?” Instead of trying to describe her
					feelings in their ambiguity and confusion, she asks “How do you feel?" The
					other, because she is trying to establish a ground of openness and trust, begins
					describing her own feelings. Thus the liar learns more than she tells.</p>

				<p>And she may also tell herself a lie: that she is concerned with the other’s
					feelings, not with her own.</p>

				<p>But the liar is concerned with her own feelings.</p>

				<p>The liar lives in fear of losing control. She cannot even desire a relationship
					without manipu- lation, since to be vulnerable to another person means for her
					the loss of control.</p>

				<p>The liar has many friends, and leads an exisence of great loneliness.</p>

				<p>The liar often suffers from amnesia. Amnesia is the silence of the
					unconscious.</p>

				<p>To lie habitually, as a way of life, is to lose contact with the unconscious. it
					is like taking sleeping pills, which confer sleep but blot out dreaming. The
					unconscious wants truth. It ceases to speak to those who want something else
					more than truth.</p>

				<p>In speaking of lies we come inevitably to the subject of truth. There is nothing
					simple or easy about this idea. There is no “the truth,” "a truth" — truth is
					not one thing, or even a system. It is an increasing complexity. The pattern of
					the carpet is a surface. When we look ciosely or when we become weavers, we
					learn of the tiny multiple threads unseen in the overall pattern, the knots on
					the underside of the carpet. This is why the effort to speak honestly is so
					important, Lies are usually attempts to make <pb n="26"/> everything simpler —
					for the liar — than it really is, or ought to be.</p>

				<p>In lying to others we end up lying to ourselves. We deny the importance of an
					event, or a person, and thus deprive ourselves of a part of our lives. Or we use
					one piece of the past or present to screen out another. Thus we lose faith even
					with our own lives.</p>

				<p>The unconscious wants truth, as the body does. The complexity and fecundity of
					dreams come from the complexity and fecundity of the unconscious struggling to
					fulfill that desire. The complexity and fecundity of poetry come from the same
					struggle.</p>

				<p>An honorabie human relationship — that is, one in which two people have the right
					to use the word "love” — is a process, delicate, violent often terrifying to
					both persons involved, a process of refining the truths they can tell each
					other.</p>

				<p>It is important to do this because it breaks down human self-delusion and
					isolation.</p>

				<p>It is important to do this because in so doing we do justice to our own
					complexity.</p>

				<p>It is important to do this because we can count on so few people to go that hard
					way with us.</p>

				<p>I come back to the question of women’s honor. Truthfuiness has not been
					considered important for women, as long as we have remained physically faithful
					to a man, or chaste.</p>

				<p>We have been expected to lie with our bodies: to bleach, redden, unkink or curl
					our hair, pluck eyebrows, shave armpits, wear padding in various places or lace
					ourselves, take little steps, glaze finger and toe nails, wear clothes that
					emphasize our helplessness.</p>

				<p>We have been required to tell different lies at different times, depending on
					what the men of the time needed to hear. The Victorian wife or the white
					southern lady, who were expected to have no sensuality, to "lie still"; the
					twentieth-century “free" woman who is expected to fake orgasms.</p>

				<p>We have had the truth of our bodies withheld from us or distorted; we have been
					kept in ignorance of our most intimate places. Our instincts have been punished:
					clitorectomies for "lustful” nuns or for "difficult" wives. it has been
					difficult, too, to know the lies of our complicity from the lies we
					believed.</p>


				<p> The lie of the "happy marriage," of domesticity — we have been complicit, have
					acted out the fiction of a weil-lived life, until the day we testify in court of
					rapes, beatings, psychic cruelties, public and private humiliations.</p>

				<p>Patriarchal lying has manipulated women both through fafsehood and through
					silence. Facts we needed have been withheld from us. False witness has been
					borne against us.</p>

				<p>And so we must take seriously the question of truthfulness between women,
					truthfulness among women. As we cease to lie with our bodies, as we cease to
					take on faith what men have said about us, is a truly womanly idea of honor in
					the making?</p>

				<p>Women have been forced to lie, for survival, to men. How to unlearn this among
					other women?</p>

				<p>"Women have always lied to each other." "Women have always whispered the truth to
					each other.” Both of these axioms are true.</p>

				<p>"Women have always been divided against each other." “Women have afways been in
					secret collusion." Both of these axioms are true.</p>

				<p>In the struggle for survival we tell lies. To bosses, to prison guards, the
					police, men who have power over us who legally own us and our children, lovers
					who need us as proof of their manhood.</p>

				<p>There is a danger run by all powerless people that we forget we are lying, or
					that lying becomes a weapon we carry over into relationships with people who do
					not have power over us.</p>

				<p>I want to reiterate that when we talk about women and honor or women and lying,
					we speak within the context of male lying, the lies of the powerful, the lie as
					a false source of power.</p>

				<p>Women have to think whether we want, in our relationships with each other, the
					kind of power that can be obtained through lying.</p>

				<p>Women have been driven mad, “gaslighted," for centuries by the refutation of our
					experience and our instincts in a culture which validates only male experience.
					The truth of our bodies and our minds has been mystified to us. We therefore
					have a primary obligation to each other: not to undermine each other’s sense of
						<pb n="27"/> reality for the sake of expediency; not to gaslight each
					other.</p>

				<p>Women have often felt insane when cleaving to the truth of our experience. Our
					future depends on the sanity of each of us and we have a profound stake beyond
					the personal in the project of describing our reality as candidly and fully as
					we can to each other.</p>

				<p>There are phrases which help us not to admit we are lying: "my privacy,“
					"nobody’s business but my own.” The choices that underlie these phrases may
					indeed be justified; but we ought to think about the full meaning and
					consequences of such language.</p>

				<p>Women’s love for women has been represented almost entirely through silence and
					lies. The institution of heterosexuality has forced the lesbian to dissemble, or
					be labelled a pervert, a criminal, a sick or dangerous woman, etc., etc. The
					lesbian, then has often been forced to lie, like the prostitute or the married
					woman.</p>

				<p>Does a life "in the closet” — lying, perhaps of necessity, about ourselves to
					bosses, landlords, clients, colleagues, family, because the law and public
					opinion are founded on a lie — does this, can it, spread into public life, so
					that lying (described as discretion) becomes an easy way to avoid conflict or
					complication? Can it be- come a strategy so ingrained that it is used even with
					close friends and lovers?</p>

				<p>Heterosexuality as an institution has also drowned in silence the erotic feelings
					between women. I myself lived half a lifetime in the lie of that denial. That
					silence makes us all to some degree, into liars.</p>

				<p>When a woman tells the truth she is creating the possibility for more truth
					around her.</p>

				<p>The liar leads an existence of unutterable loneliness.</p>

				<p>The liar is afraid.</p>

				<p>But we are all afraid: without fear we become manic, hubristic, self-destructive.
					What is this particular fear that possesses the liar?</p>

				<p>She is afraid that her own truths are not good enough.</p>

				<p>She is afraid, not so much of prison guards or bosses, but of something unnamed
					within her.</p>

				<p>The liar fears the void.</p>

				<p> The void is not something created by patriarchy, or racism, or capitalism. It
					will not fade away with any of them. It is part of every woman.</p>

				<p>“The dark core,” Virginia Woolf named it, writing of her mother. The dark core.
					It is beyond personality; beyond who loves us or hates us. We begin out of the
					void, out of darkness and emptiness. It is part of the cycle understood by the
					old pagan religions that materialism denies. Out of death, rebirth; out of
					nothing, something.</p>

				<p>The void is the creatrix, the matrix. It is not mere hollowness and anarchy. But
					in women it has been identified with lovelessness, barrenness, sterility. We
					have been urged to fill our "emptiness" with children. We are not supposed to go
					down into the darkness of the core.</p>

				<p>Yet, if we can risk it, the something born of that nothing is the beginning of
					our truth.</p>

				<p>The liar in her terror wants to fill up the void with anything. Her lies are a
					denial of her fear; a way of maintaining control.</p>

				<p>Why do we feel slightly crazy when we realize we have been lied to in a
					relationship?</p>

				<p>We take so much of the universe on trust. You tell me: "In 1950 I lived on the
					north side of Beacon Street in Somerville.“ You tell me: “She and I were lovers,
					but for months now we have only been good friends.” You teil me: "It is seventy
					degrees outside and the sun is shining." Because l love you, because there is
					not even a question of lying between us, I take these accounts of the universe
					on trust: your address twenty-five years ago your relationship with someone I
					know only by sight, this morning's weather. I fling unconscious tendrils of
					belief, like slender green threads, across statements such as these, statements
					made so unequivocally, which have no tone or shadow of tentativeness. I build
					them into the mosaic of my worid. I allow my universe to change in minute,
					significant ways, on the basis of things you have said to me, of my trust in
					you.</p>

				<p>I also have faith that you are teiling me things it is important I should know;
					that you do not conceal facts from me in an effort to spare me, or yourself,
					pain.</p>

				<p>Or, at the very least, that you wili say, “There are things l am not telling
					you."</p>

				<p>When we discover that someone we trusted can <pb n="28"/> be trusted no longer it
					forces us to re-examine the universe, to question the whole instinct and concept
					of trust. For awhile, we are thrust back onto some bleak, jutting ledge, in a
					dark pierced by sheets of fire, swept by sheets of rain in a world before
					kinship, or naming, or tenderness exist; we are brought close to
					formlessness.</p>

				<p>The liar may resist confrontation, denying that she lied. Or she may use other
					language: forgetulness privacy, the protection of someone else. Or she may
					bravely declare herself a coward. This allows her to go on lying, since that is
					what cowards do. She does not say, I was afraid, since this would open the
					question of other ways of handling her fear. It wouid open the question of what
					is actually feared.</p>

				<p>She may say, I didn't want to cause pain. What she really did not want is to have
					to deal with the other’s pain. The lie is a short-cut through another’s
					personality.</p>

				<p>Truthfulness, honor, is not something which springs ablaze of itself; it has to
					be created between people.</p>

				<p>This is true in political situations. The quality and depth of the politics
					evolving from a group depends in very large part on their understanding of
					honor.</p>

				<p>Much of what is narrowly termed "politics" seems to rest on a longing for
					certainty even at the cost of honesty, for an analysis which, once given, need
					not be re-examined. Such is the dead-endedness — for women — of Marxism in our
					time.</p>

				<p>Truthfuiness anywhere means a heightened complexity. But it is a movement into
					evolution. Women are only beginning to uncover our own truths; many of us would
					be grateful for some rest in that struggle, would be glad just to lie down with
					the sherds we have painfully unearthed, and be satisfied with those. Often I
					feel this like an exhaustion in my own body.</p>

				<p>The politics worth having, the relationships worth having, demand that we delve
					still deeper.</p>

				<p>The possibilities that exist between two people, or among a group of people, are
					a kind of alchemy. They are the most interesting things in life. The liar is
					someone who keeps losing sight of these possibilities.</p>

				<p>When relationships are determined by manipuation, by the need for control, they
					may possess a dreary, bickering kind of drama, but they cease to be interesting.
					They are repetitious; the shock of human possibility has ceased to reverberate
					through them.</p>

				<p>When someone tells me a piece of the truth which has been withheld from me, and
					which I needed in order to see my life more clearly, it may bring acute pain,
					but it can also flood me with a cold, sea-sharp wash of relief. Often such
					truths come by accident, or from strangers.</p>

				<p>It isn’t that to have an honorable relationship with you, I have to understand
					everything, or tell you everything at once, or that I can know, beforehand,
					everything I need to tell you.</p>

				<p>It means that most of the time I am eager, longing for the possibility of telling
					you. That these possibilities may seem frightening, but not destructive, to me.
					That I feel strong enough to hear your tentative and groping words. That we both
					know we are trying, ail the time, to extend the possibilities of truth between
					us.</p>

				<p>The possibility of life between us.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="publisher_note">
				<p> Adrienne Rich is a well-known poet and feminist who has published 9 books. The
					most recent one, Of Woman Born: Motherhood as Experience and Institution (W.W.
					Norton &amp; Company), she described as coming “from the double need to survive
					and to work; and I wrote it in part for the young woman I once was, divided
					between body and mind, wanting to give her the book she was seeking...." </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
