<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="undefined"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Westcote_will</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>R<ex n="£">e</ex>p<ex n="£">e</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex>itur
				<lb/>Testamentum
				<lb/>Sebastiani
				<lb/>westcote
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Sebastian Westcote's Wil1 TNA: PRO PROB 101105
				<lb/>pp 1–11* (3April: probate 14 April)
				<lb/>In the name of the moste glorious and blessed trynitie the father, the sonne,
				<lb/>and the holie ghost. so be yt./ I Sebastian westcote Almener of the Cathedrall
				<lb/>Churche of St. Pawle in London being greved with sycknes, being yet,of
				<lb/>perfect [of] mynde and memorye (to god I geve praise therefore) this third
				<lb/>daie of Aprill in the yere of o<ex n="¥">u</ex>r lord god 1582:/ And in the xxiiijth yere of the
				<lb/>raigne of oure most gracious soueraigne Ladye Cuene Elizabeth &amp;c. make my
				<lb/>last will and testament in manner &amp; fourme ensewing hereby revokyng all
				<lb/>other wylls and testament<ex n="£৳">es</ex> whatsoeuer by me heretofore made/ ffirst and
				<lb/>before all thing<ex n="£৳">es</ex> Commending my soule vnto the mercie of my saviour Ihesus
				<lb/>Christ asking pardon for all my synnes and offenc<ex n="£৳">es</ex> in his bytter death and
				<lb/>passion hoping in the last Iudgement daye to ryse and rest with this my
				<lb/>wretched bodie in his blessed kyngdome amonge his elect Comytting my
				<lb/>earthlie bodye vnto the earth to be buried at the ] discrecion of my executour
				<lb/>of this my said last will &amp; testament hereafter named/ my worldlie good<ex n="£৳">es</ex> I
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>1–6/ (. . .) also... porcions: added in l<ex n="£">e</ex>st margin and 6–7/ And further: in display script
				<lb/>keyed with a double caret to the proper place in the 25/ In the ... moste: in display script
				<lb/>text: loss of letters caused by trimming
			</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>giue and dispose as followeth/. viz. ffirst I giue and bequeath to &amp; amongest
				<lb/>the Petycannons of the said Cathedrall churche of St Pawle to bryng my bodie
				<lb/>to the Churche ffyve pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ And to &amp; amongest the vycars of the same
				<lb/>Churche to bring my bodye lykewyse to churche fower pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ And to the
				<lb/>ten Chorasters of the same Churche ffyve pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ Item I giue to gyle<ex n="৳">s</ex>
				<lb/>Clothier and Iohn Boult viz./ Gyles iij li. vj s. viij d./ And Boulte I giue fower
				<lb/>pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>./ To everye of the vergers of the same churche XS. a pece to bring me
				<lb/>to Churche/ To the keper of the vestrye iij s. iiij d./ To everie of the bellryngers
				<lb/>there iij s. iiij d./ To the poore of the p<ex n="\$৲">ar</ex>ishe of Chimley where I was borne in
				<lb/>the Cowntie of devon iij li. To the poore w<ex n="€">i</ex>thin the towne of Tawnton in the
				<lb/>cowntye of Somers<ex n="£">e</ex>t xl s./ To the poore of kyrton in devon LS./] To the poore
				<lb/>of kingstone nere Taunton aforesaid VS./ To the poore of the p<ex n="\$৲">ar</ex>eshe of St
				<lb/>gregorie neere Pawle<ex n="৳">s</ex> churche in London xx S./ To the poore prysoners w<ex n="€">i</ex>thin
				<lb/>the severall howse<ex n="৳">s</ex> and prysons called the fflete, the marshalsey, the kyng<ex n="£৳">es</ex>
				<lb/>benche, the white Lyon in Southwark, the twoe Cownters, Newgate, Ludgate,
				<lb/>Bethelem, and the gatehowse in westmynster, to everie pryson vj s. viij d. a
				<lb/>pece/ Item I giue and bequeath to the vse of the Almenerye howse of the
				<lb/>said Cathedrall Churche of St Pawle where I nowe dwell, to be &amp; remayne
				<lb/>vnto the, Tsame said Almenery howse to the vse of the Almener there for
				<lb/>the tyme beyng for ever toward<ex n="£৳">es</ex> the furnishing of the same house, my chest
				<lb/>of vyalyns and vyall<ex n="£৳">es</ex> to exercise and learne the children &amp; Choristers there/
				<lb/>And also one table in the hall withe the frame A settle of ioyned worke, a
				<lb/>paire of great Iron Aundyrons there, the table, frame and settells, hanging<ex n="£৳">es</ex>,
				<lb/>waynscot and Coubourd in the p<ex n="\$৲">ar</ex>lour there, The hanging<ex n="£৳">es</ex> in myne owne
				<lb/>Chamber, the hangyng<ex n="£৳">es</ex> in the chamber over the kytchen The great Chest,
				<lb/>and great presse there/ the Coubourd &amp; the great chest at the staiere<ex n="৳">s</ex> hed,
				<lb/>fyve bedsted<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, fyve mattresses, fyve p<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>r of blanket<ex n="£৳">es</ex> fyve bolsters of floxe fyve
				<lb/>Coverled<ex n="£৳">es</ex> suche as are acustomablie vsed for the tenne Choresters, together
				<lb/>with all suche wood and Coales as shalbe lefte in the house, exceptinge some
				<lb/>necessarye fewell for my executour for the tyme beyng there vntill suche tyme
				<lb/>as the reste of the stuff be ryd oute of the house, A pestle and morter, the third
				<lb/>brasse panne, the worser kettle, the second &amp; third brasse pott, a water Chafer,
				<lb/>the worser chaffingdishe, fyve latten Candlestick<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, the second &amp; third spytt,
				<lb/>the seconde p<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>r of Aundyrons, one p<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>r of tong<ex n="£৳">es</ex> &amp; a fyershovell of the
				<lb/>worser sorte a drippinge panne, twoe p<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>r of hangers, a trevet, three of the
				<lb/>worser platters fowre of the worser dishes, the worst skom<ex n="₱">m</ex>er, fowre poryngers
				<lb/>vj of the worst sawcers of pewter, one of the worser basons A pottle &amp; a quarte
				<lb/>pott of pewter, twoe pynte pott<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, the] worst chamberpotte/ More I giue to
				<lb/>the said Almenerye house to remayne for ever as aforesaid, twoe mazers bownd
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>9–10/ Chimley ... devon: Chulmleigh, Devon
				<lb/>19] said: intended for cancellation
				<lb/>11/ kyrton in devon: p<ex n="৲¢">ro</ex><ex n="₽">b</ex>ably Cheriton, Devon
			</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>abowte withe sylver, one bygger, and the other lesser vj sylver spoones of the
				<lb/>smaller sorte w<ex n="€">i</ex>th slyps/ All w<ex n="฿">h</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>ch said plate &amp; househould stuff so by me as
				<lb/>aforesaide given to the said Almenery house (necessarye waste onlie excepted)
				<lb/>Iwill that an Inventarie Indentyd thereof to be made, one parte whereof I will
				<lb/>shalbe &amp; remayne in the safe custodie of the worshipfull deane and Chapter
				<lb/>of the said Cathedrall churche &amp; their successours, And the other parte thereof
				<lb/>to be delyveryd vnto the Almener of the said Cathedrall churche for the tyme
				<lb/>beyng, to thentent the said deane and Chapter maye at theire pleasures call the
				<lb/>Almener for the tyme beyng to an Accompte/ And for the sure delyverie of
				<lb/>the same to his successours for ever/ Item I giue &amp; bequeath to my brother
				<lb/>george westcote xl S./ And to everye of his children xxvj s. viij d./ Item I giue
				<lb/>&amp; bequeath vnto my syster Iaquet Goodinow x li. And] forgeve all suche debt
				<lb/>as she oweth me./ Item I giue &amp; bequeath vnto Elizabeth westcote wydowe my
				<lb/>syster in Lawe twentie pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, together with the Lease of westgrene w<ex n="฿">h</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>ch
				<lb/>Inowe have, and all ye household stuff, and kyene &amp; Cattell there./ Item I
				<lb/>giue &amp; bequeath vnto my brother Robert westcote xiij li. vj s. viij d./ And I
				<lb/>forgeve him all suche debt<ex n="£৳">es</ex> as he oweth me/ To Andrew westcote his sone
				<lb/>x li.] And to everye of his other children xxx S./ Ite<ex n="₱">m</ex> I giue vnto Roger westcote,
				<lb/>Sebastian and ffrawnce<ex n="৳">s</ex> westcote sonne<ex n="৳">s</ex> of my late brother william westcote,
				<lb/>to everye of them x li., allowyng suche thing<ex n="£৳">es</ex> or somes of money I owe them*
				<lb/>Ite<ex n="₱">m</ex> I giue to the daughters of my syster Iaquet Goodinow iij li. a pece, beinge
				<lb/>fowre of them/ Item I giue &amp; bequethe to my systers daughter w<ex n="฿">h</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>ch was
				<lb/>[married of late] marryed of late, toward<ex n="£৳">es</ex> the buylding of her howse w<ex n="฿">h</ex><ex n="€">i</ex>ch
				<lb/>was bvrnt vj li. xiij s. iiij d./ And to her twoe children xx S. apece/ Item Igiue
				<lb/>&amp; bequeath vnto ffrydiswide Clunye, widowe nowe beinge in howse with
				<lb/>me, the some of x li. and] the fourth featherbed p<ex n="£৲">er</ex>fourmed./ Item I giue to
				<lb/>Margarett Riche my syster in lawe xl s. in money./ Ite<ex n="₱">m</ex> I giue to lohn Thornley
				<lb/>and his syster ffraunc<ex n="£৳">es</ex> xxx S. apece. Ite<ex n="₱">m</ex> I geve to Henry Redford, &amp; to
				<lb/>Elizabeth ffarthing dwelling att Bierton on the Countie of Buck<ex n="£৳">es</ex> if they be
				<lb/>living at the tyme of my decease xx S. apece/ Item I giue to bartholomew
				<lb/>Redford xxx S./ Item I giue to Richard my man xxx S./ Item I geve to katheryn
				<lb/>my mayde servaunt iij li./ Item I giue to Thomas Bluet, Thomas Barsey,
				<lb/>Robert, and Iohn Aundersone nowe remayning in my howse to everye of them
				<lb/>V li. apece/ Item I geve to peter phillips likewise remayning w<ex n="€">i</ex>th me vj li.
				<lb/>xiij S. iiij d./ Item I giue to Thomas venge iij li./ Item I giue to bromeham,
				<lb/>Richard Huse, Robert knight, Nicholas Carleton (<ex n="₽">b</ex><ex n="₮">l</ex><ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="₭">n</ex>k) Baylie (<ex n="₽">b</ex>l<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="₭">n</ex>k) Nasyon,
				<lb/>&amp; gregorye Bowryng sometymes children of the said Almenerye howse, to
				<lb/>everie of them xx S. apece/ Item I giue &amp; bequeath to the right worshipfull
				<lb/>m<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="৳">s</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex><ex n="£">e</ex>r Iustice Southcott ] my especiall good frend my gilt Cupp w<ex n="€">i</ex>th the
				<lb/>cover having on the Cover St Sebastian/ Item to my lovyng frend mr Henry
			</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Evans vj li. xiij s. iiij d./ and a lytle Cuppe of sylver &amp; a cover w<ex n="€">i</ex>th ij lytle
				<lb/>ring<ex n="£৳">es</ex> on the cover/ Item Igiue to westcote that ys blynde iij li./ Item to my
				<lb/>frend Iustynian kydd gent<ex n="₮">l</ex><ex n="£₱">em</ex><ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="₭">n</ex> a square sault gilted wroughte./ And whereas
				<lb/>I the said Sebastian westcote have in this my last will and testament given
				<lb/>&amp; bequeathed vnto dyvers of the Children of my brothers &amp; systers and to
				<lb/>other my frend<ex n="£৳">es</ex> children all or the most parte of them nowe beyng verye
				<lb/>yonge and so by lawe not hable to dischardge my executour of the receight
				<lb/>of suche legacie<ex n="৳">s</ex> as I haue given vnto them/ my will and meanyng is, that if
				<lb/>it shall happen anye of the said children to be putt fourthe apprentyces, that
				<lb/>the m<ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="৳">s</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex><ex n="£">e</ex>r &amp; parent<ex n="£৳">es</ex> of everie suche childe puttyng in sufficient assurance to
				<lb/>my executour to dischardge him against them &amp; everie of them for the same
				<lb/>shall haue the Legacie of everye suche childe as by good discrec<ex n="€">i</ex>on of my
				<lb/>executour shalbe thought best ] for the benefytt of suche childe or children/
				<lb/>Item Igiue &amp; bequeathe to my<ex n="৳">s</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex>res Good wydowe, latelye the wief of doctour
				<lb/>Good Physicion a ryng of gold w<ex n="€">i</ex>th a blew stone, and to her dawghter
				<lb/>kynborowghe a ryng withe three lemmowes small/ To mystres Sowthcote a
				<lb/>gold ryng of some pretye fasshion to be made for her to the value of xl s./ To
				<lb/>mr Iohn Sowthcot<ex n="£৳">es</ex> wief the yonger a lyke ryng of gold of xl s. price. The
				<lb/>resydew of all my good<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, Cattell<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, money, plate, Iewell<ex n="£৳">es</ex>, with my debt<ex n="£৳">es</ex> to
				<lb/>me owynge not heretofore given &amp; bequeathed (my debt<ex n="£৳">es</ex> paid &amp; this my
				<lb/>testament accomplished and p<ex n="£৲">er</ex>fourmed, and all other necessarye expenc<ex n="£৳">es</ex>
				<lb/>and Charg<ex n="£৳">es</ex> from tyme to tyme that my executour shalbe at satisfied allowed
				<lb/>and paid) I whollie geue &amp; bequeath porcion &amp; porcion lyke amongest the
				<lb/>children of my brethren and systers/ And thexecutour of this my last will &amp;
				<lb/>testament I make &amp; ordayne my lovyng frend Iustinian kydd gent<ex n="₮">l</ex><ex n="£₱">em</ex><ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="₭">n</ex> to 2
				<lb/>whome for his frendlie paynes herein to be taken I giue Tenne pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ And
				<lb/>overseer of the same I make my foresaid deare frend mr Henry Evans prayeng
				<lb/>him to be assisting] to my executour with his good Councell, and lykewise
				<lb/>to be Carefull for my syster Elizabethe westcote wydowe in her affayres and
				<lb/>busyne<ex n="৳">s</ex> as tyme shall serve/ In wytnes whereof I the said Sebastian westcote
				<lb/>to this my last will &amp; testament have putto my hand &amp; seale the daye &amp; yere
				<lb/>abouewrytten/ wytnesses at the sealyng &amp; delyvering hereof/ Signed sealed &amp;
				<lb/>delyveryd as his last will &amp; testament the daye &amp; yere abouesaid as his deed
				<lb/>in the presence of mr Creake, Robert Nycholles, Iohn ore, and Raphe Parys
				<lb/>gent<ex n="₮">l</ex><ex n="£₱">em</ex><ex n="\$">a</ex><ex n="₭">n</ex>, by me Thomas Creake/
				<lb/>Legacie<ex n="৳">s</ex> given by the saide Mr Sebastian westcote after the sealyng subscrybing
				<lb/>and delyvering aforesaid the sayd third of Aprill/ To lohn Ore, more then is
				<lb/>conteyned afore tenne shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ To Edward Coop<ex n="£৲">er</ex> the Innocent in my
				<lb/>howse Six pownd<ex n="£৳">es</ex> thirtene shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex> fowre pence To william Gafford fyve
				<lb/>shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ To mother Alyce Tenne shillyng<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ To mother Smaley tenne
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>12/ good: preceded by apparent false start for b or 1
			</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ To mother walker tenne shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>./ To Pole the keper of] the gate
				<lb/>tenne shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ By me Thomas Creake. Ro<ex n="₽">b</ex><ex n="£৲">er</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex> Nicolles Radul<ex n="₴">p</ex><ex n="฿">h</ex> Paris/ Iohn
				<lb/>Ores mark.
				<lb/>Tercio Aprilis Anno predicto/ More he gave after, theis Legacie<ex n="৳">s</ex> aforesaid/ To
				<lb/>everie of mr Raphe Paris Children Tenne shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex> a pece/ To Shepard that
				<lb/>kepeth the dore at Playes tenne shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ More to George Paris tenne
				<lb/>shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex> to make it vp twentye shillyng<ex n="£৳">es</ex>/ Ro<ex n="₽">b</ex><ex n="£৲">er</ex><ex n="૱">t</ex> Nicolles.
				<lb/>The said testator after the making of his said will gaue to Catheryne his maid
				<lb/>for that shee tooke greate paines w<ex n="€">i</ex>th him in his sicknes more then he gave
				<lb/>her in this former will forty shilling<ex n="£৳">es</ex>./
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>17/ This . .. made: in display script
				<lb/>24/ Wittnesseth: in d<ex n="€">i</ex>splay script
				<lb/>21/ Betwene: in display script
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>