<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Aragon_entry_records</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id="Aragon_entry_records-0001.jpg" n="1"/>
			<div>
				<head>APPENDIX 6: <lb/>Royal Entry of Katherine of Aragon, November 1501</head>
			</div>
			<div>

				<p>This appendix provides examples, from manuscript records of the royal entry of
					Katherine of Aragon in November 150I (see Appendix I), of the types of entry
					records not normally transcribed for The Records but included as references
					either in explanatory notes to the transcribed records or within diamond
					brackets below the relevant dated listings in Appendix 1. Such records appear in
					the main body of the collection only when interwoven in the manuscripts with
					records of theatrical activity or music. Largely such excluded records involve
					one or more of riders to meet the entrant at his/her approach to the city, the
					rails behind which companies stood along the entry route, the standings (or
					platforms, including rails) upon which they stood, the breaking and subsequent
					repairing of the pavement where the standings rails were placed, costs of food
					and drink, sand or gravel laid down on London Bridge and in the streets (to
					cushion the horses hooves and prevent them from sliding), gifts, detail of
					liveries worn, debts for riding costs, fines of those absenting themselves from
					riding (attendance on these occasions being normally compulsory for company
					members), and other such non- musical, non theatrical elements of these
					occasions. (For the cushioning of horses' hooves, see Leland,Collectanea, vol 4,
					p 10.) Such elements were standard for major entries, and many of them also for
					more routine entries not usually involving theatrical and for which there are
					normally no records of music (although trumpets, at least, must almost nvariably
					have been used). Also, although approvals of assessments to cover costs at royal
					entries have been included within The Records, detailed collection arrangements
					and arrears, such as those transcribed below from Repertory I, are normally
					merely cited in endnotes or in Appendix 1 listings.</p>
				<p>Katherine of Aragon and Prince Arthur (heir to the throne of England) had been
					married to one another by proxy in May 1499, but Katherine's arrival in England
					had been delayed until late 1501, when finally she arrived at Plymouth on 2
					Qctober. A lengthy progress to London then took place, with the royal entry
					through the city (from Lambeth) on 12 November and the wedding at St Paul's on
					14 November. On 16 November the court moved by water from the city to
					Westminster, for celebrations there with tournaments, banquets, and the like. On
					26 November a civic escort accompanied the court up the river from Westminster
					to Mortlake (adiacent to Richmond). (See the main records transcribed under
					1499-1500, 1500-1, and 1501-2:, also Appendix I under 1501-2 (12, 14, 16, and 26
					November) and the ODNB.) The events preceding and following 12 November were <pb
						n="2"/> not part of the royal entry through the city, but company
					non-musical, non-theatrical records of them have nevertheless been included
					below because, relating to the same period pf celebration, they extend the range
					of examples of records not typically included within The Records.</p>
				<p>Several of the records require the provision here of additional information. For
					an explana- tion of the last line of the items from Repertory I, see the related
					Mercers Company's record below. The manuscript heading (not transcribed) for the
					payments from f 32v of the Bakers' Company's accounts states that this account
					is for two years, 15 and 16 Henry VII (that is, 22 August 1499 to 2I August
					1501)' since the company's accounting year generally runs from one 23 November
					to the next, and the record concerns the 12 November royal entry, the heading
					almost certainly indicates 23 November 1499-23 November 1501. In the first
					Brewers' Company record, a list of sixty-four names, at 6d each, precedes the
					tota transcribed. The third Brewers' record refers to jousts, records of
					tournaments or joustings which do not mention either music or theatrical
					elements such as role-playing are by standard REED policy excluded from The
					Records, and in any case these specific [ousts are at Westminster. The Drapers'
					Company's record of barge hire to Westminster with the king is internally dated
					20 November; after the wedding on 14 October the court, as noted above,
					travelled by water to Westminster on 16 November (see Appendix 1), so either the
					20th is a payment (not event) date or (much less likely) there was another
					occasion on the 20th requiring an escort. A Drapers' record of payment
					concerning the water escort to Mortlake is included in The Records because
					referring to music, and is also dated later than the date, according to other
					sources, of the occasion itself.</p>
				<p>The reference to Southampton in the Grocers; Company's payments transcribed is
					related to Katherine of Aragons' arrival on 2 October at nearby Plymouth; she
					was supposd to have landed at Southampton (see Kipling, Recyt, p 115). In the
					items from the Skinners' Company's accounts, the reference in the second-to-last
					payment to all the times includes not only the occasions mentioned in the
					payments transcribed but also the occasions of the hire of barges to Westminster
					for the sheriff's presentation in September 1501 and for the mayor's oath-
					taking in October 1501 (both occasions with transcribed records in the main body
					of this collection). The transcribed record from f 60 of the Wiresellers'
					Company's accounts is followed in the manuscript by a list of names and sums,
					but no total is provided, and not all of the individuals listed may be providing
					money for this particular purpose; after the first eight names come three
					without a sum (one of which is deleted), and of five further names, one is
					paying for two or three years, one for two years past, one in part payment of a
					fine, and one for this year.</p>
				<p>The Goldsmiths' Company was no doubt heavily involved in the receiving of
					Katherine of Aragon, since goldsmith John Shaa was mayor of London in November
					1501. A manuscript record (Goldsmith's Hall: MS 1520, p 385) of fines for two
					individuals absent when the company 'ffetched the prynce &amp; pryncesse frome
					Grenewiche' does not seem, however, to be related to the entry, and the record
					has therefore not been included below. No editorial headings have been supplied
					for the records other than those in the manu- scripts themselves. The records
					have been ordered as in any one year of The Records. <pb n="3"/> For all
					document descriptions, except for the Wiresellers' Wardens' Account below, see
					The Documents.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Wiresellers' Wardens' Accounts</head>
				<p>The accounting year runs most often from one November to the November two years
					later, for the Pinners, and apparently August/September to August/September in
					either two-year or three-year spans, for the Wiresellers. Further detail on the
					contents of the manuscript is provided in the BL Catalogue of Additions, vol 8:
					1846-1847 (1864), 197-8.</p>
			</div>

			<div>
				<dateline>1501-2</dateline>
				<head><title>Court of Aldermen, Repertory I</title>
					<bibl>LMA: COL/CA/01/01/001</bibl></head>
				<pb type="folio" n="90"/>
				<gap/>
				<p>¶Eod<ex>e</ex>m die <note>Eod<ex>e</ex>m die: 2 December</note> dat<ex>us</ex>
					est dies cuilibet Ald<ex>e</ex>r<ex>mann</ex>o ad inportand<ex>a</ex>
						arreragi<ex>s</ex> enarior<ex>um</ex> assess<ex>orum</ex> sup<ex>er</ex>
						ward<ex>as</ex> suas erga aduent<ex>um</ex> d<ex>omi</ex>ne
					kat<ex>er</ex>ine filie <note>filie: e correctect over j</note> Reg<ex>is</ex>
					<del>e</del> lspanie die louis p<ex>ro</ex>x<ex>imo</ex> sequent<ex>i</ex>
					<del>s</del> &amp; hoc sub pena inprisonamenti </p>

				<p>M<ex>emora</ex>nd<ex>um</ex> Cl<ex>er</ex>ici M<ex>aioris</ex>
					<del><gap/></del> &amp; vic<ex>ecomi</ex>t<ex>um</ex> erunt
						contribut<ex>ori</ex>y Ad om<ex>ni</ex>a on<ex>er</ex>a &amp;c.</p>

				<p>
					<handShift/>Adnull<ex>atum</ex> postea Ad Cur<ex>iam</ex> t<ex>empor</ex>e Rest
						M<ex>aioris</ex><handShift/></p>

				<p>It<ex>e</ex>m Considerat<ex>um</ex> est q<ex>uo</ex>d cl<ex>er</ex>ici
						cur<ex>ie</ex> Maior<ex>is</ex> et cl<ex>er</ex>ici computa<add
						place="above">to</add>rior<ex>um</ex>
					<note>computa<add place="above">to</add>rior<ex>um</ex>: for computato</note>
					<del>de</del> nec non s<ex>er</ex>uient<ex>es</ex> et valecti Maioris et
						vic<ex>ecom</ex>t<ex>u</ex>m de cet<ex>er</ex>o er<ex>u</ex>nt
					contributorijs ad o<ex>mn</ex>ia onera assess<ex>a</ex> sicut alij ciues
						s<ex>e</ex>c<ex>un</ex>d<ex>u</ex>m facultates suas <del>se</del> ita tamen
						q<ex>uo</ex>d de vigilijs &amp; cet<ex>er</ex>is officijs viz.
						const<ex>ahu</ex>l<ex>arijs</ex> et similes <note>similes: for
						similibus</note> penit<ex>us</ex> exon<ex>er</ex>abu<ex>n</ex>t<ex>u</ex>
						ffin<ex>is</ex>
					<add place="above">xx<hi rend="superscript">ti</hi> li.</add> assess<ex>us</ex>
						sup<ex>er</ex>
					<del>s</del> Mistera<ex>m</ex> Merceror<ex>um</ex>
				</p>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<pb n="4"/>

			<div>
				<head><title>Armourers and Brasiers Wardens Accounts</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/AB/B/001/MS12065/001</bibl></head>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>f 26v 24 June 1501-24 June 1503</head>
				<pb type="folio" n="26v"/>
				<gap/>
				<table>
					<row>
						<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m payd for brekyng of the pament In cornell when ye lady
								kater<ex>i</ex>ne come to london</cell>
						<cell>viij d.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m payd to Richert smythe carpynt<ex>er</ex> for makyng of
							ye Rayll<ex>es</ex> for ye standyng</cell>
						<cell>xiij s. iij d.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m payd for di. a C of vj dj. nayll for ye Rayll</cell>
						<cell>vj d. ob.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m payd for caryg<ex>e</ex> of the same Rayll</cell>
						<cell><gap/>j d</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m payd for a lode of gravell</cell>
						<cell>iiij d. <note>iiij d.: probable reading; sum not clear</note></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m payd for st<gap/>ys for ye pament</cell>
						<cell>vj d.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m payd for the <gap/>yng of the same pament</cell>
						<cell>ij s.</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head><title>Bakers Audit Book</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/BA/B/001/MS05174/001</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="32v"/>
					<head>f32v (1490-1501) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m for the takyng vp of the pament where yo<ex>ur</ex>
								standding was the tyme the princes came oute of spayne in to london
								vj d. lt<ex>e</ex>m p<ex>ai</ex>d to tho<ex>m</ex>as A wode
									Carpent<ex>er</ex>. for xv. yearrd of lengithe Closid be
									fo<ex>ur</ex> &amp; be hynd be Cavse of pres of the peopill
								.xij. s. S<ex>u</ex>mma</cell>
							<cell>xij. s. vj d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m for the pavyng &amp; dreshing of the same pament
								Ageynne</cell>
							<cell>iij. s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<div>
				<lb/>
				<head><title>Brewers' Wardens' Accounts</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/BE/B/001/MS05442/001</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="page" n="8"/>
					<head>p [8] of 1501-2 account Rendered 21 February 1502/3)</head>
					<ab>Mony Ress<ex>e</ex>₻<ex>ea</ex> ffor Stondynge in cornell xxjj ss. [vj
						d.]</ab>
					<ab>lt<ex>e</ex>m the Seid Accom<ex>m</ex>pta<ex>u</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> Chargeth
						them Selff w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> certayn mony by 3 them Ressaued of
							dyu<ex>er</ex>s p<ex>er</ex>sonez beyng in the leu<ex>er</ex>ey of Blew
						toward the cost<ex>es</ex> made And Raled in Cornell at com<ex>m</ex>yng In
						of the lady princez kat<ex>er</ex>yn king<ex>es</ex> doughter of Spayn
						Maried to arthur p<ex>r</ex>ince of ynglon</ab>
					<gap/>
					<ab>S<ex>u</ex>m<ex>ma</ex> xxxij s.</ab>
				</div>
				<div>
					<pb type="page" n="15"/>
					<head>p [15] of 1501-2 account Customary expenses)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m Paid ffor Makyng of A Raile for the hole Company of
									o<ex>ur</ex> crafte made by lohn Clerk Carpent<ex>er</ex> In
								cornell At Ressauyng of my lady princez kat<ex>er</ex>yn secund
								doughtan <note>doughtan: for doughter</note> vnto kyng of Cspayn
								Maried vnto Arthur P<ex>ri</ex>nce <note>P<ex>r</ex>rince: e
									corrected over another letter</note> of Inglond he first son of
								kyng h<ex>enr</ex>y vij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
								<note>vijth: v corrected over s or f</note></cell>
							<cell>xliiij s. xj d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
				<div>
					<pb type="page" n="17"/>
					<head>p [17] of 1501-2 account (Costs of various dinners)</head>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>ffirst cost<ex>es</ex> made of A den<ex>er</ex> vnto the hole
								Company In th lyu<ex>er</ex>ey beyng p<ex>re</ex>sent with [the] Sir
								lohn Shaa knyght thei Maire In takyng his othe At
									westm<ex>inster</ex> the Barons of th kyng<ex>es</ex> escheker
								then kepyng ther co<ex>ur</ex>t at that tym<ex>e</ex> In the
									syng<ex>es</ex> Stondyng then at that tym<ex>e</ex> ordendyned
								and mad for the lust<ex>es</ex> at the Mariage of p<ex>ri</ex>nce
								Arthur And Tat<ex>er</ex>y secund dought<ex>er</ex> of kyng of
								Spayn</cell>
							<cell>liiij s. vj d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head><title>Carpenters Wardens Accounts</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/CC/D/002/MS04326/001</bibl></head>
				<pb type="folio" n="90v"/>
				<div>
					<head>f 90v 15 August-15 August) (Hall payyments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m p<ex>ai</ex>d for xxiiijti yard<ex>es</ex> of Rayle
								for the Crafte to stand in At the Comyng of the prynses of
								spayne</cell>
							<cell>xvj s. viij d. </cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m p<ex>ai</ex>d for pavyng of the holys there the
								Rayle stode</cell>
							<cell>ij s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head><title>Drapers' Wardens' Accounts</title> DH: MS WA2</head>
				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="72"/>
					<head>f 72(c 15 August–c 15 August) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m to Crosby Carpenter for the fraym in Chepe where we
								stod at the com<ex>m</ex>yng in of the p<ex>ri</ex>nces dame kateryn
								ovte of payne <add place="above"><handShift/>lxxx in our
										lyu<ex>er</ex>ey.<handShift/></add></cell>
							<cell>xxx s.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m for drinking money to the Carpenters at diuers
								tymes</cell>
							<cell>viij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>lt<ex>e</ex>m for Bargehire to Westm<ex>imnster</ex>
									w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the king the xx<hi rend="superscript"
									>ti</hi> day of Nouembr<ex>e</ex></cell>
							<cell>xiij s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>

				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>

			<pb n="6"/>
			<div>
				<head><title>Founders Wardens Accounts</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/E/B/001/MS016330/001</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="page" n="47"/>
					<head>p 47(16 September-16 September) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m paid for the standyng of our Compeigny]g] and pavyng
								of the ground</cell>
							<cell>xxj s. <del>v</del>ij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head><title>Grocers Memorandum, Ordinance, and Account Book</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/GH/A/006/MS1 1570A</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="page" n="95"/>
					<head>p 95 (19 July-18 July) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m for Costis of two p<ex>er</ex>sons Riding to
								Southampton</cell>
							<cell>iij li. iiij s. viij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m for makyng of Raill<ex>es</ex> in Chepe at the
								princess comyng</cell>
							<cell>v li. xj s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m in Expens<ex>es</ex> the same tyme</cell>
							<cell>xij s. vij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m for Cost<ex>es</ex> goyng to Richemount
									w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the princesse</cell>
							<cell>xlj s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head><title>Ironmongers Register</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/1B/B/001/MS116988/001</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="87"/>
					<head>f 87(15 July 1501- 15 July 1503) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<ab>Whan The Prynses was Rec<ex>ei</ex>₻<ex>ea</ex> yn to london</ab>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>ffyrste payde to A Carpynter for to make A frame for The
								felyschype to stande yn to se her S<ex>u</ex>m<ex>m</ex>a</cell>
							<cell>x s. vj d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Item payde to iiij laborers for A daye to set yt wpe</cell>
							<cell>xx d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Item payde for Caryinge of the tymber And Borde</cell>
							<cell>viij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Item payde for naylynge of the Same</cell>
							<cell>vij d. ob</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Item payde for brede and Ale Candylle &amp; for scharpyn, of þe
								ssryn</cell>
							<cell>viij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Item payde for pavynge a gen of the Strete</cell>
							<cell>ij s. iiij d.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>

					<lb/>
					<ab>S<ex>u</ex>m<ex>m</ex>a xvj s. v d. ob./</ab>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head><title>Mercers' Acts of Court</title> MH: Acts of Court 1</head>

				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="122v"/>
					<head>f 122v (17 December)</head>
					<p> [symbol]Where as diu<ex>er</ex>s p<ex>er</ex>sones of oure lyu<ex>er</ex>ey
						com not to the barge when the kynges good grace went from
							Westm<ex>imster</ex> to Mortelake/ and also som that come late/ where
						thorough grete displeasure was taken by my lorde Mayre &amp; my Maisters
						thaldermen In so myche they in a Courte holden at the <pb n="7"/> yelde hall
							m<ex>er</ex>cyde oure felishipp for the said trespas at vj li. xiij s.
						iiij d. for the repayment of the same it is agreed that it shalbe levied
						uppon suche p<ex>er</ex>sones as were warned and made defaute &amp;c</p>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head><title>Skinners Receipts and Payments</title>
					<bibl>LMA: CLC/L/SE/B/007/MS30727/001</bibl></head>
				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="156"/>
					<head>f 156 (10 June-26 May) (Payments)</head>
					<gap/>
					<table>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m paid for the hyre of a Bote of vj owers to accompany
								ane to attende vpon the prynces from london to Westmynst<ex>er</ex>
							</cell>
							<cell>vij s. vj d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m rewardyd the Botemene and for brede and Drynk spen
								vpon theym and o<ex>ur</ex> company</cell>
							<cell>xviij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m for the hyre of a grete Bote to Wayte vpon the
								prynces rom Westmynster to Rychemond</cell>
							<cell>xv s. vj d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m rewardyd the Botemen</cell>
							<cell>xviij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m paid for Rysshes for the said Barg<ex>es</ex> and
								Botys by all the said tymes</cell>
							<cell>xij d.</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>It<ex>e</ex>m paid for o<ex>ur</ex> Scaffold stondyng in Chepesyde
								ayenst the commyng yn of the prynces to london</cell>
							<cell>xl s.</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<gap/>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head><title>Wiresellers' Wardens' Accounts</title>
					<bibl>BL: MS Egerton 1 142</bibl></head>

				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="58v"/>
					<head>f 58v (1501-4)</head>

					<ab>It<ex>em</ex> payd to thomas A wod Carpynter ffor makyng off owr skaffowlld
						A yen the prynces cam in v s. j d. and to the laboras ffor makyng off the
						hollys ffor the tymbyr and ffor the stopyng A yen ij s. ij d.</ab>
					<ab>[t<ex>em</ex> payd att ij tymes [fo] to the karter ffor bryngyng owr [(.)ey]
						stuff ffron Ihon Allssopp one tyme iiij d. the second tyme iij d</ab>
					<ab>It<ex>em</ex> payd ffor the hangyng up of owr clothys And bestoyng <lb/>off
						owr stuff ...d.</ab>
				</div>
				<gap/>
				<div>
					<pb type="folio" n="60"/>
					<head>f 60</head>
					<ab>Receued off the brether to the makyng off the skaffolld in Cornell ayen the
						prynsses cam.</ab>
					<note>followed by a list of 8 contributions totalling 11s 4d</note>
					<gap/>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
